Finding Aid for The American Hotel and Al's Bar Project records LSC.2305
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Correspondence, circa 1981-2004
  - The Andy Warhol Foundation letter, 1994 December 22 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    Correspondence from Program Director Emily Todd to Marc Kreisel concerning his proposal for the Andy Warhol Curatorial Program Grant. Kreisel proposed the Museum of Graffiti Art (MOGA) as a pilot program under the non-profit umbrella of A.N.T.
  - Office of the City Attorney letters, 1994-1995 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    Letters to Kreisel from the Los Angeles City Attorney investigators demanding payment for the removal of "Illegally Posted Signs on Public Property."
  - Priority Records letter, 1996 January 12 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    Correspondence to the Al's Bar booking agent concerning the "up and coming" band, Mention.
  - Stoughton fax, 1997 January 13 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    Facsimile to Marc Kreisel regarding approval of the Live at Al's CD label art work.
  - Hayden's Ferry Records fax, 1997 April 11 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    Facsimile confirming Surf Ballistics "bringing their hard groove funk" to Al's Bar on April 27th.
  - Rachel Kreisel fax, 1997 June-August (Box 11, Folder 21)
    Al's Bar facsimile and supporting environmental health inspection documentation concerning rodent harborage, cockroaches, peeling paint, missing toilet tank cover, missing soap, toilet paper dispensers, cobweb removal, hole in the ladies room wall near toilet, peeling paint in the men's toilet room, and general cleaning throughout the space.
    In a September 7, 2016 email correspondence with Kelly Besser, Rachel Kreisel shares a bit of her backstory which includes meeting The Mister, Marc Kreisel:
    "I started in broadcasting, working in radio as an audio engineer. When I started around 1972, it was pretty much unheard of for women to work the technical end of broadcasting which is why when I applied at CBS they gave me a typing test. I first worked at KPFK and was there through the whole SLA/Patty Hearst dust up. Then I moved over to KABC/KLOS where I stayed until 1989. I spun discs with the DJs at KLOS then moved over to talk radio, the last 5 years as Michael Jackson's engineer. I later had a brief stint producing a show for KPPC.
    After leaving radio I worked in film for a couple of years as an assistant editor then story analyst. But the work was spotty, so a friend told me about a non-profit, L.A. Shares, that dealt with schools and the art community and was looking for an office manager. The place gave away stuff donated by movie studios and other businesses to other non-profits; paper, office furniture, odds and ends.
    So Marc came in one day with his band of merry men from Al's National Theatre looking for props. I took one look at Marc and said, 'If I know one thing, I know this is not the guy for me.' But he was such a happy upbeat guy and everyone looked like they were having so much fun. So I went to work for him. I sat in the hotel office watching the drama of the tenants play out and knowing I had my subject (my Dublin, if you will). Those were the stories I wrote for S.A. Griffin. That also got me a PEN fellowship and a Pushcart nomination.
    But I also realized that the whole place had something to say about the intersection of art and business, how this guy navigated the intricacies of the city bureaucracy, kept the place going on no money and still managed to make and believe in art. He was also the only person I'd met who believed that making art in any form was important and if that's what you were driven to do, that's what you should do. What can I say, it was irresistible."
  - Joel Bloom letter, 1998 January 28 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    Letter from Joel A. Bloom, President of the Los Angeles River Artists and Business Association to City Councilman Richard Alatorre concerning the following Arts District issues: improvement of public transit via DASH stops, official Arts District public signage, and the reevaluation of Artist in Residence ordinances.
  - Al's Inc. fax, 1998 March 28 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    Facsimile of Marc Wint Kreisel's selected exhibition history, references, and writings as Irene Greenberg, Critic at Large.
  - KBA Marketing letter, 1998 July 3 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    Correspondence from KBA City Manager Lorin Denker to Marc Kreisel of Al's Bar regarding the enclosure of the third installment for the wall mural.
  - Postcards, 1998 August 27, 2000 January 5, undated (Box 11, Folder 25)
    Postcards to Toastacia Boyd requesting band bookings at Al's Bar.
  - Kerry letter, circa 1990s (Box 11, Folder 26)
    Letter and Murder at Millies! comic from Kerry to Sherri.
  - Mark Goodman fax, 1999 September 15 (Box 11, Folder 27)
    Facsimile to Toastacia Boyd regarding Magnet's inability to play Al's Bar on November 3rd or 4th.
  - KBA faxes, 2000 January, July, August (Box 11, Folder 28)
    Facsimiles between KBA Marketing and Marc Kreisel concerning Camel sponsorship of Radio Free Al's DJ Slam and Dance Party on August 22, 2000 with the following DJs: Miss Sugar, Miss Nicobra, Skatemaster Tate, Marcel Dejour, Vinzula, The Scottfather, The Bear, and Bumper.
  - Marc Kreisel letters, 2001 August 16, 20 (Box 11, Folder 29)
    Letters from Kreisel to Michael Meraz of Magnum Properties concerning locking Kreisel out of Al's Bar, destruction of property, harassment, intimidation, threats, the disposal of artwork, and falsehoods about the bar closing which appeared in the Los Angeles Times on August 16, 2001.
  - Bar theft letter, circa 2001 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    Anonymous letter to Marc Kreisel apologizing for taking the door to Al's Bar. The writer states, "When we took it, we really believed that we were saving a little piece of Al's Bar from the wrecking ball."
  - Re: Peter Plagens recommends, 2002 March 26 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    Electronic mail print out from Rosamund to Marc Kreisel with the subject line regarding Peter Plagens recommends.
  - Whitney Museum letter, 2004 January 12 (Box 11, Folder 32)
    Letter to Marc Kreisel from the Whitney Museum of American Art concerning the return of photographs to Kreisel.
  - Al's Bar mailing lists, undated (Box 11, Folder 33-34)
    Mailing lists include handwritten names, addresses, zip codes, and email addresses of artists and patrons. The lists contained within folder 34 include the heading: "I KNOW YOU'RE DRUNK BUT P PLEASE TRY TO BE E LEGIBLE!"
  - Al's Bar press lists, undated (Box 11, Folder 35)
    Lists include addresses, phone numbers, fax numbers, and names of contacts.
  - A.N.T. lists, undated (Box 11, Folder 36)
    This folder contains Al's National Theater press lists, call sheets, and a Christmas show list.
  - American Hotel stationery (Box 11, Folder 37)
    One blank sheet of American Hotel stationery which includes its address.
  - Al's Bar fax cover letter (Box 11, Folder 38)
    One blank Al's Bar fax cover letter includes the bar's ubiquitous anthropomorphized brick graphic.
  - Toastacia Boyd stationery (Box 11, Folder 39)
    Blank sheet of stationery personalized for Al's Bar booking agent Toastacia "Toast" Boyd. This folder also contains the cut and paste original used for its creation.
  - Al's Bar address stamp (Box 12)
    One address stamp and two Al's Bar Inc. stamps.
- Financial records, 1980-2003
  Financial records include checking statements, deposit slips, check stubs, wage reports, tax returns, vendor receipts, permits, licenses, and bills.
  - Al's Bar checking statements, 1989-1990, 1992-1996 (Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Folder 1-3)
    Box 13: Folder 1 contains a sample of Al's Bar City National Bank deposit tickets and folders 2-7 contain Al's Bar Inc. First Los Angeles Bank checking statements (1989-1990, 1992-1994 May).
    Box 14: June 1994-March 1996.
    Box 15: April 1996-December 1996.
  - Lease Masters checking statements, 1993-1996, 2000-2001 (Box 16, Box 17, Box 15, Folder 4-6)
    According to Rachel Kreisel, Lease Masters is the entity that ran the American Hotel.
    Folders contain First Interstate Bank checking statements and accompanying checks.
    Box 15: January 1993-April 1994.
    Box 16: June 1994-November 1996.
    Box 17: November 1996-December 1996, January 2000-November 2001.
  - Deposit slips and check stubs, 1989-1996, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 1-2, Box 18)
    These records document the financial activities of the American Hotel, Al's Bar, and Al's National Theater.
    Box 18: 1989-1995.
    Box 19: 1995-1996, 2001.
  - American Hotel records, 1980-2002 (Box 19, Folder 3-18)
    Materials include a bound book of American Hotel financial documentation, grant deed, profit and loss statements, tenant lists, legal documents, community development loan paperwork, Small Business Administration disaster assistance application, Traction Avenue Development Project proposal, Al's National Theater checking statements, A.N.T. summary financial report, Al's Bar receipts, and tallies.
  - Tax documentation, 1986-1987, 1989-2003 (Box 19, Folder 19-20, Box 20)
    Box 19: State Board of Equalization and payroll documents (1997-2001, 2003).
    Box 20: U.S. Corporation Income Tax Returns, payroll tax returns, sales and use tax returns, wage reports, State Board of Equalization audit documentation, and Internal Revenue Service documents (1986-1987, 1989-2003).
  - Vendor receipts, 1991-2000 (Box 21, Folder 1-22)
  - Permits, licenses, and bills, 1988-2002 (Box 21, Folder 23-36, Box 22)
    Box 21: 1988-2002.
    Box 22: Conditional Use Alcoholic Beverages maps (1987). Folder 2 includes a floor plan for Al's Bar with notes for fire department regulations and renovations (1989).
- Memorabilia
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This series contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the file levels. All requests to access processed audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  Memorabilia includes photographs, stickers, Live at Al's CDs, the bar's cash can, jukebox records, beer taps, t-shirts, signs, and a microphone.
  - Bar taps (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
    Four beer taps removed from the bar represent the following brews: Red Dog, Red Hook ESB, Sierra Nevada Pale Ale, and Beck's.
  - Microphone, circa 1996 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Cash can (Box 24, Folder 1)
    According to Rachel Kreisel, this cash can was the workaround from the bar's cash register. The bartenders put all the twenty dollar bills in the can and the rest of the money went into the cash register.
    This Al's Bar rusty cash can is plastered with stickers which include Popdefect, the Cubs, and Hunger Farm.
  - Propellor (Box 24, Folder 2)
    According to Rachel Kreisel, "The American Gallery had a Christmas show every year for maybe 10 years which showed work from local artists priced at around $100, you know, affordable for the holidays. To the best of Marc's recollection, he bought this piece from one of those shows, but he has no recollection of the artist."
    This American Gallery art piece is constructed with a propellor, fabric, and some electrical wires.
  - Al's Bar t-shirt screens (Box 25)
    Small screen for Al's Bar "what a dive" and larger screen for Dirk Vermin's "Fox" design.
  - Al's Bar t-shirts (Box 26)
    Box contains twelve t-shirts with various designs.
  - Al's Bar t-shirt designs (Box 27, Folder 2)
    Designs for silk screens include Al's Bar "She males available" by X-Ray Designs, Al's Bar what a dive, Al's Bar The Line between Art & Life, and Al's Bar Downtown Tip or Die.
  - Photographs (Box 28, Folder 1-9, Box 27, Folder 3)
    Box 27: One oversize color photograph of the walls inside Al's Bar.
    Box 28:Images include a black and white photo of Marc Kreisel by Gary Leonard, Al's Bar staff, Al's Bar DJs, the American Gallery, Jeff Goldblum's sister's exhibition at the American Gallery, an Al's National Theater polaroid of Mayhem at the Mayfield Mall III, The Golden Turkey Awards Polaroids, Al's Bar by Marc Kreisel, The American Hotel, and bands at Al's Bar.
  - Al's Bar CDs, 1996 (Box 29, Folder 1, Box 28, Folder 10-15)
    Box 28: Three copies of the Live at Al's compilation compact disc, an artist list, CD cover art work, one CD cover, and The True Story of Al's Bar liner notes.
    Box 29: One unfolded Live at Al's CD cover without matches.
    BOX 28 CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this box will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
    - Al's Bar What a Dive, undated; yrlsc_2305_028_015; 1 sound recordings (1 CD) (Box 28, Case 15)
      CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are available for access. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
      Content note: Al's Bar Live CD Compilation
  - Al's Bar Certificate of Appreciation, 1999 March 6 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    Certificate presented by The Alliance to Preserve Los Angeles Downtown Arts District and Action: Space for the Los Angeles Downtown Arts District Urban Design Competition.
  - Stickers (Box 28, Folder 17-20)
    These stickers were removed from the walls of Al's Bar.
  - An Authentic Piece of Al's Bar plaque, circa 2001 (Box 28, Folder 21)
    The text along the plaque's border reads, "ThelinebetweenartandlifeThelinebetweenartandlife." The dominant engraved text reads, "An Authentic Piece of Al's Bar Love Al. 1979-2001."
  - Al's Bar jukebox record art, 2004 December 15 (Box 28, Folder 22)
    Design of Big Brother and the Holding Company (1968) "Piece of My Heart" 45 rpm 7-inch single.
  - Who's a Jew? exhibition cards, 1994 (Box 28, Folder 23)
    Cards publicize Marc Kreisel's one person show opening reception at Julie Rico Gallery 2623 Main St. Santa Monica 90405 on Saturday, July 9th from 9-11 pm.
  - VHS tapes, 1981, undated (Box 28, Folder 24-25)
    One VHS tape is labeled Young Turkeys and the other, Al's Bar. The Young Turkeys VHS is a video that was cut together from all of the tape shot during The Golden Turkey Awards. This folder also contains a DVD of The Young Turkey Awards created by Marc "King" Kreisel and an Al's Bar the Movie Pt. 1 DVD.
    Two VHS tapes.
    BOX CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this box will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
    - Young Turkeys, 1981; yrlsc_2305_028_024; Yanemoto, Norman; Kreisel, Marc; Hugo, Joan; Ottinger, Bee; 1 video recordings (1 VHS; Duration: 0:49:33) (Box 28, Case 24)
      The Young Turkeys VHS is a video cut together from footage shot during The Golden Turkey Awards. Presenters and winners speak; guests are interviewed. Written on a label on the spine of the cassette is, in all caps, "Young Turkeys"; no other markings exist on the tape. On the case is a yellow sticker that reads "MASTER W/O#" followed by a faded number, and below, the logo for and name "Lightning Dubbs"; elsewhere on the case are a couple handwritten strings of numbers.
    - Al's Bar, 1981; yrlsc_2305_028_025; Kreisel, Marc; 1 video recordings (1 VHS; Duration: 0:07:54) (Box 28, Case 25)
      The Al's Bar VHS comprises a comedy sketch set inside Al's Bar with multiple characters playing various roles--most notably, a young woman (holding "an MBA from USC, 1999") wandering through the bar looking for "Al's School of Bar Management." Written in white on the front of the cassette is "AL'S BAR"; there are no other markings on the cassette or its case.
  - Young Turkey books, 1981 (Box 29, Folder 2-3)
    Five bound black books filled with color Polaroids that document The Golden Turkey Awards. Two of the books include captions for these photographs.
  - Al's Bar jukebox records (Box 30, Box 31)
    These boxes contain singles on vinyl from the Al's Bar jukebox. The bar's jukebox played music from hundreds of artists and bands such as the B-52's, Tony Bennett, Blondie, Marc Bolan, David Bowie, James Brown and The Famous Flames, Johnny Cash, Petula Clark, The Clash, Devo, Shirley Ellis, Marianne Faithfull, Al Green, Aretha Franklin, Generation X, Marvin Gaye, Merle Haggard, Jimmy Hendrix, George Jones, Janis Joplin, Chaka Khan, Redd Kross, Peggy Lee, Teena Marie, Meat Puppets, Joni Mitchell, Pop Defect, Prince, The Psychedelic Furs, Queen, Sex Pistols, Dee Dee Sharp, Frank Sinatra, Siouxsie and the Banshees, Patti Smith Group, The Smiths, The Supremes, Talking Heads, Doris Troy, Tina Turner, and X.
    These singles are arranged alphabetically by artist.
    Box 30: 1000 Mona Lisas -- Loretta Lynn. There is no record in the Carole King "One Fine Day" sleeve.
    Box 31: The Manhattan Transfer -- The Zombies.
    Two hundred and eighty-eight 45 rpm 7-inch records.
    BOXES CONTAIN AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in these boxes will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - Al's Bar porthole pattern (Box 32, Folder 1)
    One circular piece of wood used as a "pattern" for the nautical porthole in the front door of the bar.
  - No Graffiti sign (Box 32, Folder 2)
    This sign hung with irony behind the bar.
    This municipal sign includes a red circle around with a slash through the word Graffiti. The text beneath reads "Graffiti is Against the Law" and includes Penal Code 594 text.
  - Musicians road sign (Box 32, Folder 3)
    This yellow and black diamond crossing sign features silhouettes of a musician family running hand in hand. The leading member with a beret holds a guitar and a smoke, the next in a skirt with a camera around her neck holds a paintbrush, and finally a kid with pig tails holds a spray can.
    This sign hung behind the bar and was designed by John the Minor, also known as John E. Miner. This design was used for the Al's Bar "Twenty Years and Running" t-shirts.
  - Tip or Die sign (Box 33)
    This neon sign hung behind the bar and illuminates these words: Tip or Die.